OK, Larry.
Let's go ahead now with
the rest of your story.
And pick up where we stopped
with the army service.
Yes, I'm in the army.
And like I said before,
I created a little bit
of a hardcore around myself.
And we found out that
the ghetto does not have
bread for two days already.
And there is no sign.
We're not permitted to
leave to go out and buy,
or there is no sign of
improvement at this point.
So I called in some of my guys.
And we sit down and,
what can we help?
The decision was
made that we are
going to see if we can take
bread from our soldiers, what
we have from our Jewish boys,
and deliver to the ghetto.
Somehow, the word
got to the general
that we are planning
to take some bread.
The word got to
him was like this.
We got up early in the morning.
And we packed a
wagon full of bread,
and we threw hay and
straw on top of it,
and put those forks
in it, to make
it look like we are
traveling to deliver hay
to another section of the city.
And two guys got on
the top and drove out.
But one of the sergeants
observed it, and saw everything
we are doing.
So he went to the
general and told him
that the Jew boys stole
bread and went out with it.
He doesn't know where
we went with it.
But we stole a wagon of bread.
So he saw me.
He called me in.
And he says to me, you know, I
have a real charge against you.
I can arrest you right now.
I should arrest you, he says.
You stole a wagon of bread.
I says, no, I didn't
steal the bread.
We took it to the other
section to where our boys are,
and they needed
hay for the horses.
He says, hay, I understand.
But since when are the
horses eating bread?
And bread in such
a big demand now.
Then he says, don't lie to me.
Tell me the truth.
What did you do with the bread?
So I says, well, we
took it into the ghetto.
There's some of our
people are hungry.
We need bread.
He said to me, I don't
want to hear about it.
And he says, and
the next time he
says, if you want to do
something don't be a dumb Jew
and let yourself being caught.
I saluted him.
And I said, yes sir.
And turned around
and walked out.
The next day we already
managed, we already found out.
So he was actually
sympathetic towards--
He was helping.
He's trying to help.
That was--
And then two days later, again,
we went in with one wagon.
And then he saw
me during the day.
And he calls me in, and says to
me, did you make your delivery?
I said, yes sir.
He says, job well done.
And I went away.
But things deteriorated
very badly.
Do you have any idea
this man's name?
I haven't written down at home,
his son, I have the address.
I have a letter from his son.
I'm in contact with his son.
I have his picture.
I have everything.
OK, let's go ahead.
And things deteriorated in
the city, and out of town.
And the Hungarians didn't--
the population
didn't like that we
as Jews who have been sitting
outside and sleeping outside,
and instead of being
confined to the camp.
So one day he came in
and arrested all of us,
and threw us in the ghetto.
Well, they took you
out of the service
then, and into the ghetto.
And then throw it
into the ghetto.
OK.
We ran away from the
ghetto, back to the--
again after three or four
days, there was no food.
Myself, there is
another guy here.
He lives right
here in Cleveland.
His name is Leonard Fox.
He was with me at the time.
We ran back in to the army,
took some breads in bags,
as much as we could.
I remember I had 14 loaves, and
I think he had the same amount.
And we were caught
by bringing them in.
He got beaten up very badly.
They gave him 45 lashes.
He passed out.
And by the time they got to me,
I somehow managed to run away,
jumped over, went away, and
I hid myself in the fields.
And he didn't see me.
But came at night, I
didn't know what to do.
I decided I better go
back in, in the ghetto.
Because if I would
be on the street,
as the curfew is on the street,
the first thing they'll do
is shoot me.
Sure.
So I didn't want
to take a chance.
I thought my chances of
survival are better there.
So I went back
in, in the ghetto.
And that was my mistake.
Without knowing,
the next morning,
we were all rounded
up, put on the train,
and away we went to Auschwitz.
Everybody in the ghetto, or
just you who were involved?
Everybody.
The whole ghetto
was cleared out?
The entire ghetto
was liquidated.
OK.
I see.
The entire ghetto was
liquidated, put in, in trains,
and off we went to Auschwitz.
You went to Auschwitz.
Now, all right.
Now can you tell me, what were
your experiences in Auschwitz?
Were you with your family?
No.
I have heard--
That's right.
You were-- I had forgotten.
I haven't heard
anything from my family.
I don't know anything what's
happening with my hometown.
Right.
The only thing we
heard is the rumors
they have all been taken away.
We don't where.
Sure.
Do you remember how long this
train ride was from the town
where the army camp was
that ghetto, to Auschwitz?
How long were you on that train?
Well, the ride took
us about five days.
We used to stop
once or maybe twice,
and receiving some water.
We are not permitted
to get out of it.
Just one guy may be jumping
out and filling dishes with
and passing him water,
no food, just water.
No food, whatsoever.
Was this-- were
these regular trains?
Were these cattle trains?
What kind of trains?
No.
It was-- let me explain.
It was a train
with cattle wagons.
In other words, they were
like boarded in all around.
But it wasn't the
passenger trains?
No, no passenger trains.
No, no, no.
It was commercial.
They were freight cars.
Freight cars.
Absolutely, freight
cars like you pushed in,
80 to 100 people in one sitting
one on top on the other one.
They came the families.
They let the
families be together.
But since I had no
family, nobody with me,
so we so to speak, the whole
hardcore guys were together
again, half of it anyhow.
And we went, stick
together, and we went.
That's the way we
arrived to Auschwitz.
OK.
The screams, the
cries, the pushing,
the shoving in the
train those five days,
I don't know if there is any
human being can describe them.
Terrible.
The cry from the kids, the
smell from older people
and from young children.
And you name it.
And it's hard.
I don't think there is anything
to describe it, just to say
it's terrible is not a word.
I don't think there is a
word in the dictionary that
would fit the description.
What was your
experience in Auschwitz?
Now, we are arriving
to Auschwitz.
And there, the minute the
train pulled in and stopped,
it's like there would
be a complete new world.
Like you would
fall to the bottom,
will fall out of everything,
screams, the doors opened.
Do you recall the date?
The date it was, two
days before, Shavuot.
Let's see.
That would be--
In May.
That would be in around
the 26th of May, 1943.
This was when you were taken
from the ghetto and put in.
And within that five day period
are your arrival in Auschwitz.
Yes, right.
OK.
Describe your
arrival in the camp.
In the camp, like I said
before, like it's a new plant.
They opened up the doors,
the screaming, raus!
The barking of the dogs,
and jumping the dogs,
the SS holding back,
they jump-- the dog
from jumping on anybody.
And those big sticks
and black uniforms
with a Totenkopf, the
death hats on their--
it is impossible to describe.
And the screamings, and the
pushing, and the shoving, raus!
Eintreten, raus,
eintreten, which means out.
In line, out, get in
line, out, get in line.
That's all.
And then kids lost--
babies lost their mothers.
Mothers lost their husbands,
and fathers lost their children,
and screaming.
Everybody looking for everybody.
And the dogs barking.
Finally everybody found
everybody, got in line.
Now, we are walking.
They separate men on one
side, women and children
on the other side.
Nobody in his wildest
dreams would ever
imagined that this
is the last time
that they will see each other.
Sure.
Now as we got in line,
put us in a line,
men separated, women separated.
This has to be a terrible
feel-- you had no idea what
the future held for you.
We don't see nothing.
We don't--
You're told you're going--
You are so preoccupied with
the events at the moment
that your mind doesn't
even wander away.
Your mind is right here.
But of course, it's
a question for what
is the next moment coming.
When you were put on
that train, did you
know where you were going?
No, no idea.
No idea.
OK.
And when you stopped and
you saw the soldiers,
we don't where we are.
You don't know what's going
to happen to you from one
moment to the next.
We don't know where we are.
We don't know what's happening.
The minds-- excuse me--
are so occupied just
to be from the moment.
Sure.
Finally, we are in a line,
and we start walking.
And there we see three
SS, all beautiful dressed,
fancy clothes, shiny
boots, like a mirror.
Later, we find out
it was Dr. Mengele.
And he's standing there
and like this, you walk up.
And you're supposed
to tell them your age.
You come to him and you say
16, 17, 18, whatever, 50, 20,
whatever your age is.
Sure.
I came in front of him.
I said, 17.
[NON-ENGLISH] 17.
He looked at me and
makes like this,
means I'm going to the right.
Other guys, to the right,
to the right, to the right.
Then he makes like this.
It means to the left.
We didn't know the meaning
of it, what it means.
Of course not.
Left and what it
means to the right.
And finally it's over,
so to speak, that--
Selection.
--selection.
We got in.
And now we are lined up
men, only men, no woman,
no children.
They are all separated
in a different direction.
We are lined up eight
in a line, and a whole
on the back, a whole line, I
don't know how many thousands.
And I'm in the middle.
And we are about to walk.
From far, I can see there is
a big sign through a gate.
And it says, Arbeit
macht frei, which
means work brings liberty.
So to go through
that gate, as we
are walking towards the gate,
on both sides are barracks.
Are you carrying
anything, any possessions?
I just have one--
on my back, I have a sack with--
A rucksack, a knapsack.
Yeah, right, a
knapsack, with some,
a few of my personal
belongings, nothing else.
And as we are walking,
somehow I had the feeling
that somebody is looking at me
and that something will happen.
I looked around, and
I didn't see nobody.
But I saw one SS man, soldier
walking with a big stick
and with a whip in his hand.
And I saw him walking,
more I came closer to him,
and closer he came
to me, somehow
something in me starting
to work harder and harder.
And from out of the blue sky--
It was fear.
No, it was-- I can't
describe the feeling,
and it was something.
No fear, I wasn't afraid
of anything in those days.
Sure, you were a young
healthy, young man.
It's something--
Something's going to happen.
Something special--
something is about to happen.
And he came over closer to me.
And as soon as he came a
few steps away from me,
our eyes met, and he
had a whip in his hand.
And he started to hit
me, saying [NON-ENGLISH]..
What does that mean?
It means the damn dark, move,
that you further comes away
from here, disappear,
go, hit me a few times.
And I was just about ready
to drop my rucksack, the bag,
and just ready to jump on him.
When one of my friends in
the back, grabbed me and says
don't get crazy.
Not now.
Another time now.
He hold me back and we walked.
And this is happening so fast.
And I have to keep
on walking in line.
And as I am walking, a
thought came to me, why me?
Sure.
Here I am, I'm
walking in a line.
With so many.
So many people and
that particular feeling
after me, if he had come
in line, hit this guy,
hit that guy.
Yeah, hit this Jew.
So hit me too, so tough luck.
But why hit me?
And I just turned
around automatically,
and I was just passing the
gate to going into the camp.
It's just from walking I was
just about passing the gate,
I looked around and
I said, no matter
what you SOBs will do to me, I
will survive, no matter what.
And something
overcame me and kept
me going through all my troubles
I had for the rest of my life,
till this day.
It's something in me.
OK.
There's something that I--
I don't know what it is.
Isn't that something?
And that helped me
further, you'll see.
So here we are.
We are in the camp.
The first thing we come in,
of course, the hollering,
the pushing, the shoving.
You know, and all of that.
It's undescribable.
And then we see this guy.
And I say, hey.
I am here.
I just arrived
yesterday, the other day.
Guys from different towns.
Where is my sister?
Your sister arrived.
She is there.
We have seen her last night
on the other side of the wire,
that kind of stuff.
Right, right.
And here we are.
Did you find any friends?
Oh, yes, I had the group of my--
Well, I met other,
but not from home yet?
Oh, yes.
I'll-- I haven't
found anything yet.
I'm still in, in my own clothes.
Finally, we walk in.
We go in to take a shower.
So we're going to
bathe, to take a shower,
take off everything, and
leave it on this side.
And they say to us when you come
out, you'll pick it back up.
We know damn well
that we are not
going to come out
on this side again,
that everything what we leave
here is going to be left.
Sure.
So anyway, we left
everything here.
We went out on the other side.
The only thing we were
allowed to take is the shoes.
Everything was left.
We went out on the other side.
They gave us a shirt,
a pair of underwear,
and a pair of those
prison clothings.
Yes, right.
And you had your own
shoes, snow shoes.
Got dressed, they took us
out in front of a barrack.
That's the first time we
learned the real McCoy, what's--
That you're prisoners.
That what we are and what it is.
Right away, they
gave us a number.
They cut our hair,
everywhere, everything.
They gave us a number.
From now on, 8485.
That was your number.
That's my number.
And you don't call you by name.
They only call the number 8485.
And you say, here.
You know, and all that.
OK.
They bring us, give us
everybody, we got a--
I don't know how to call it.
We called it a shissel.
A canteen, a little pot.
It's not a canteen.
It's a pot.
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean a little tin dish.
Tin dish.
So that you-- to eat from.
They threw in some stuff in it.
Nobody could ever have eaten it.
Nobody, nobody.
Terrible.
No taste, no, we threw it away.
After three days, he got hungry.
He got used to it.
And we had to drink it.
Sure.
So, we used to get
that stuff once a day.
Bitter water, it looked
like tea in the morning,
nothing with it.
In the evening, we used to
get a ration of bread, which
is take a pound bread,
divided in four,
you get one rash, two
slices of margarine,
and one slice of slice of jelly.
That was our daily--
Your daily ration.
--ration.
And we had to live on this.
So we have been sitting outside.
We didn't know
what's going on what.
Second day, somebody says to
me that in the next barrack
there are boys from my hometown.
I went to see them.
And sure enough, there
were boys from my hometown.
And they all say, Larry.
Your dad left yesterday.
Where did he leave to?
A transport went to Warsaw.
And he is in Warsaw.
This is already after the
liquidation of the ghetto.
It's already 1944.
And this is after the
liquidation of the--
Of the Warsaw.
The Warsaw-- and in '43,
they liquidated the ghetto,
and after the liquidation of the
ghetto, he was taken to Warsaw.
OK.
I says, who else is there?
They says, your uncle was there.
And this friend, and this
friend, and his father, and all
of that.
All right.
I don't know anything.
They are going to Warsaw.
The next day, they pass
us by, no nothing happens.
You're not doing anything.
You have no routine yet?
No, nothing.
You're just sitting around.
Sitting around, and
you know, nothing,
talking what's going
to be, where do we go.
And in the meantime, we have
a smell, we feel a smell.
And we don't know
what the smell is.
Then we learn.
They showed us the chimneys.
They said, this is your parents
going through the chimney.
This is the crematorium there.
This is the smell.
And we thought, eh.
We didn't believe it.
Couldn't be, nobody
could be so inhuman.
Yeah.
That's [NON-ENGLISH] who was
going to do something like
that.
But one thing everybody said,
get out of Auschwitz as fast
as you can.
The third day, I
again met another boy.
He tells me the same story.
My father was here and he
left with the transport.
He went to Warsaw.
In the evening, rumors
started to spread
that tomorrow morning there is
a transport going to Warsaw.
And it's going to be
from a different block,
not where I am, but
the other block.
So I went over.
And I found somebody who had
a friend in the other block.
Names didn't mean anything.
Numbers didn't mean anything.
It's just the
numbers, the count.
In other words, if
you counted 50 people,
you had to have 50 people.
That's all what counted.
The rest didn't mean anything.
So we changed He came over
here, and I went over there.
And to make the
long story short,
the next day, sure enough, got
up in the morning to appell.
Eintreten, and, so a day
later, 24 hours later, I
was in Warsaw.
And sure enough,
there was my father.
Why were they sending
you to Warsaw?
To the same place,
to work where those,
the transport from
my father before.
Oh, I see.
Oh, so they sent you to a
work place, to work there.
Yes, to the same working force.
I see.
OK, I didn't realize.
So all right, so actually
then, you left Auschwitz.
You really weren't
there maybe a week.
Less, one day less than a week.
OK.
One day less than a week.
Then you went to Warsaw.
We went on the same transport,
and they took us to--
I didn't know.
I took a gamble.
But he said, Warsaw, so I said.
Right.
And it turned out, yeah.
As soon as I walked
in the camp, I already
recognized my hometown people.
OK, now what was the
name of this camp?
Was it a camp?
No, it was not.
It was like a camp, but
it was in the ghetto
where the Warsaw ghetto
was on the same place.
I see.
But it didn't have
a name or anything?
No, nothing.
Just--
So you saw people
from your town.
Just, and I saw people
from my hometown.
And they all started to
say your father is here.
Your father is here.
So I felt.
How wonderful.
I felt not bad.
Now how long had it been since
you had left your family?
I left my family, it was
six weeks, I haven't seen
and I haven't heard from them.
That's all the time it
was from the army to--
Right.
From the time you left
home, it's only six weeks?
Yeah.
OK, I just wanted
to get a time--
Late April, same year,
till after Passover.
Right, I understand.
OK.
So here I am.
And we waited till after we
had to stay in line, after we
were dismissed.
I was with my father and, he
right away he starts crying.
And you know, and he says to
me the rumors about the kids.
And then he says,
ah, it's only rumors.
And he says, and on the
other hand, I know he says,
they're eating well and
they're drinking well.
OK.
But I met another boy,
who the fact of the matter
is he is here in
Cleveland too, who is
a Polish boy, also in the camp.
I don't know where I am.
I only know it's Warsaw.
I don't know what it is, where
I am, except that Warsaw.
Excuse me for interrupting you.
Did your father,
when he was there,
did he know where his wife
and your sisters were?
Yeah, he didn't know anything.
They were in Auschwitz.
They are in Auschwitz.
That's all.
OK, that's all he knew.
And he-- yes.
And he said--
That's where they separated
the men from the women.
Right.
OK.
The events were the
regular process.
And he said that
somebody told them
in Auschwitz they are going
to get bread, white bread,
and they will live yet.
I mean live good, and
there was no problem.
All right.
And they will survive.
It's just a matter of time.
Yeah.
I already knew the
truth, but I didn't
want it to hamper with him.
I didn't want to take away his
hopes, and to make them misery.
And I thought to myself, as
long as he lives in that world,
let him live in it.
Right.
So here again,
the things started
to go different directions.
After being there for
three days doing nothing,
the fourth day, and I
came out at the weekend,
and started out on
a Monday morning.
We were called
out to go to work.
Our job was to clean bricks
from the broken buildings
and put them together on
trains, which in turn took them
to the Russian front
to build bunkers
for the winter for
the German army.
OK.
Walking through the
streets from the job,
and from the job I read all
kinds of Jewish signatures,
Jewish sayings.
[NON-ENGLISH].
What does that mean?
We were betrayed.
I was here.
Like graffiti written on walls.
Yeah, on the walls.
OK.
All right.
And I saw a street
[NON-ENGLISH],,
and another name of a street.
I didn't know.
I know that's Warsaw.
But I didn't know--
You didn't know that
this was the ghetto that
had been destroyed.
Right.
OK.
And I saw the big walls, and
I didn't know all of that.
We didn't understand.
You probably didn't even know
there had been a ghetto there.
Right, we didn't know that.
Right.
So after going on like this two
weeks, finally we found out,
we came in contact
with the Polish people
there who have been
working, and being paid
by the Army for the Germans.
They said that this is the
section where the ghetto was.
And then one day, we went
from a different direction.
I passed by a big house.
There was a big sign
saying Judenrat.
So then I knew
that we were there.
So that was like
a Jewish council.
Judenrat, that was the
Jewish Council, right.
Yeah, the headquarters of
the Jewish Warsaw ghetto
Jewish council.
Right, OK.
So here I am, in
my wildest dreams
when I have dreamed
that here after six
months after the liquidation
of the Warsaw ghetto,
I'll be in there in
the Warsaw ghetto.
So we worked there.
One day, a German
comes over and he says,
a guard comes over and
he says, [NON-ENGLISH],,
which means who knows
how to read Yiddish?
So we had a saying.
And we had a rule.
Never volunteer for anything,
and never try to be alone.
Try to stay with
more people together.
Because whenever
anything happens,
first the fear is not there.
There's a lot of psychology
involved with that.
Nobody says nothing.
Then he says, [NON-ENGLISH].
There must be somebody be
who knows how to read Jewish.
You know?
So finally I said, yes.
I raised my hand,
and I says, yes.
So he comes and takes me away
and he says, come out here.
He calls me over.
I walked with him.
So another soldier comes
with him, one of the guards.
And I said uh-uh.
That's it.
And he took his machine gun off
from his hand, and we walked.
So some of my friends
said, that's it.
So he calls me aside,
and he takes me in front.
There's a bunker like
going down to the ground.
And it's with red paint to me.
Years later, down to me
that wasn't red paint.
It was blood.
But it looked like
dried paint, you know?
And you touch it, it falls off.
You know how?
Sure, flakes off.
Right.
And it was written in
Jewish, in Yiddish,
it was written [NON-ENGLISH]
What does that mean?
In other words,
we were betrayed.
Remember us.
Later on, I found out that was
the headquarters of Anielewicz
and the whole gang of the
headquarters of the group who
fought to the last one.
So you translated that for him.
Yes, and I translated
it for him.
So he says to me,
what does it mean?
So I told him it means we were
forgotten, and remember us.
And he took me back there.
And it was over.
No problem.
OK.
They gave us cigarettes.
We had the ration.
We had no-- so to speak,
besides the pushing
around and the hollering
in the usual way,
but nothing of the brutality.
Was it all men?
All men, no woman.
Nothing of a nature
of a brutality.
Were they Germans who
were guarding you?
Oh, yes.
There were Germans there
were Yugoslavs guarding us.
There was Polish
who was guarding us.
But they were civil to you.
Under the circumstances,
I would say, yes, nothing
of a cruelty or nothing.
OK.
And the first
cruelty I entered was
one of my friends developed an
infection in one of his ears.
And some of the boys
said, don't go nowhere.
As long as you have it, stay.
Some of them said go to the
doctor and let them look at it.
He went to the doctor.
He took a chance.
The doctor looked
at him, and he says,
well, you got a bad infection.
There is nothing.
I have no medication.
There is nothing I can do.
Just take an aspirin.
He give him an aspirin.
But he needed antibiotics.
Well, there's nothing
I can do for you.
He got a high fever.
So the long story to make short,
he took him to the hospital.
There was a section that
he called a hospital.
He said, goodbye.
And that's the last time
I have ever seen him,
the last time I
ever heard of him.
Till this day, I don't know
what happened to him, how
he was killed or what.
But he disappeared.
That's it.
So that's the first encounter.
Second encounter was
a few days later,
an SS, a sergeant major, and
the rank of sergeant major
arrives on a motorbike.
And he says, we are
standing outside
in the field on the apellplatz.
And he says, good morning.
[GERMAN], who speaks German?
So several guys
raised their hands.
I was there too.
My father says, no don't go.
Don't go.
But I already raised
my hand, so I couldn't.
So he goes forwards,
to come forward.
I came forward.
He went to all of them through.
He came to me.
And he says to me,
how old are you?
[GERMAN]
I was siebzehn, 17.
He says, [NON-ENGLISH].
You'll be OK.
You'll do.
He says, come with me.
This was 1944?
Yeah.
In the beginning of '44.
Spring '44.
He says, come with me.
So you were really 19.
No, I'm already 18.
OK, whatever.
OK, yes, now I'm 18.
All right, he says come with me.
That was before my birthday.
All right, fine.
Yeah.
Achtzehn, yeah.
18.
Come with me.
So I went with him.
And he takes me to the front.
And he says there, he talks to
the sturmführer or something.
And then he says, come.
And I always, when you were
in camp and you talk to them,
you're not putting your hat on.
Your hat must be down.
So he says, put your hat down.
I put my hat down.
He says, sit in the
back of my motorbike.
So--
Were you wearing this
still this same uniform?
Sure, I was in uniform all the
time, the Auschwitz uniform.
Yeah, the prisoner uniform?
Yes, the uniform.
With the number here 845.
it's all the time,
nothing changed.
So he takes me and we
go several side streets.
And then he takes
me in a building.
And the building is bombed out.
But it's boarded
in from all over.
In other words, you
know like the windows.
They were all boarded in.
And it's a cold feeling to it.
It's something, it's like the
shivers and you walk in there.
I walk in.
And it's around, a big
building surrounded all around,
and in the middle it's
like a parking space.
There are trucks, cars,
half tracks, half tanks,
and all of that.
And it's bustling with
people coming and going.
And so he comes, takes me
in one of the sections,
takes me up and opens up a door.
And it's a big section
part of the building.
And there are dogs.
There are a dozen dogs.
And they're all barking,
and they're just
if he opens the
door, I'm finished,
they'll tear me apart.
And there is one dog
walking right behind him.
So he says to me in
German, he says, look.
He shows me.
There is a cage.
Between every dog
there is an empty cage.
There are cages.
There's two dogs, but in between
them is always an empty cage.
So he says to me like this.
You take this.
Open up this cage,
and open here.
This dog goes in here.
You close it back.
You clean this out,
put back in the food,
put in back the clean.
You open it up, the
dog goes back in.
And you open this--
So this was your new job.
Right, it was my job
to clean the cages
and give the dog the food.
And he says, you give
the dog the food.
But you don't eat his food.
He says, because you're
going to have plenty of food.
I says, fine.
[NON-ENGLISH].
Yeah.
Then he says to
me this dog here,
you can walk this way till
there, there was a line.
You can walk till there,
if you walk over the line,
there's a red line,
the dog will kill you.
And you can walk this
way till the red line.
If you walk over, the
dog will kill you again.
You know what kind
of dogs these were?
They were German shepherds,
but they were big--
Big dogs, big mean dogs.
Very mean.
They were-- some of them were
in black, and some of them
were-- it was the real McCoys.
And he said, if you go
this way, he'll jump you.
The only way you
can go is this here.
To do your job.
Yeah.
And he's going to
walk behind you.
And he's not going
to do anything.
They trained a dog.
They didn't need a person.
You can walk around any
place you want here,
but you cannot go there because
you'll jump you, and all that.
You can't cross the line.
The dog came and smelled me
a little bit and all that.
And so he says, I'll
come check with you back
in a [NON-ENGLISH],, which
means in about an hour.
OK.
He came back in an hour
and he looked around.
He liked what I saw.
But doing the work,
I had a funny smell,
like a sweet smell that
I smelt in Auschwitz.
But I thought, ah, it
can't be the same smell.
It must be that from the
dogs, the stuff and all that,
the food, and the
odor and all that.
It must be from the dogs.
But somehow, I didn't I had a
funny feeling that it's not.
Well anyhow--
Well, this was on the
site of the Warsaw ghetto?
Yeah, inside, where the
Warsaw ghetto used to be.
Yeah, right.
OK.
So I'm doing.
He comes back.
He looks at the job.
He says, job well done.
And it's lunch time.
He says, everybody's
eating lunch already.
He says you come with me.
He takes me to
the [NON-ENGLISH],,
to the kitchen there.
And he goes in and he says
to the guy in the kitchen,
[NON-ENGLISH] big
man, give him to eat.
So he comes up and he
says, [NON-ENGLISH],,
do you like noodles?
I says, yeah.
Oh, so.
OK.
He brings me out a big
bowl loaded with noodles.
Why were they so good to you?
Me, because I worked there.
So for a working man, you know?
So I ate the noodles.
I couldn't eat up all of that.
So I just put in
my shirt down here,
and you're going to take it
to somebody who's hungry.
Took to my father,
I throw it in here.
You didn't know what
tomorrow was going to be.
Then he says to me,
stick around for a while.
And you help me clean my
[NON-ENGLISH],, the big kitchen.
And he says, I'll give
you some more to eat.
I said, fine.
I waited.
About a half an hour, the
other guy says to him, yeah,
[NON-ENGLISH].
The dog was next
to me watching me.
I cleaned up
everything beautiful.
He liked it.
He gave me a big canister, like
this loaded with chunks of meat
and all kind of macaroni.
And it came around 3 o'clock,
he says, come with me.
Put me on the bike, and
drove me back into the camp.
And that was been
going on like this
for about three or four weeks.
That's what made me survive
with my father and all that.
You brought food back.
I had plenty of food.
And I gave it to my uncles,
and some of my friends.
We had plenty of what to eat.
I couldn't get
rid of that smell.
And I says to my father, I don't
understand what's going on.
There is a smell.
And that taste of
the smell bugged me.
Sure.
It didn't let me.
And I know I had
smelled it somewhere.
One day, I don't know, after
being there for a while,
somehow he took the dog away or
something happened to the dog.
I can't explain how it happened.
The dog wasn't present
for quite a while.
And I heard some things
going on behind one wall.
I couldn't figure
it out for days
I knew that something
is going on.
So I thought then the
army is coming and going.
Sure.
Curiosity killed the cats.
And I wish I had never gone.
I wish I had never walked over--
Been curious.
I walked over.
And there was, they
had three cars.
In those days, the Germans used
to have like they have now,
the cars, the vans, big
vans like the parcel post
office is carrying, you know?
Sure.
Locked in, no windows, nothing.
They had like this,
colored in black.
And the Germans used
to pick up whoever
they were to pick up, the SS.
And threw them in, in those
wagons, and bring them there.
Meanwhile, your father and the
other people in this ghetto
were working too.
Yeah, they were working.
They had different jobs.
Yes, they have been
cleaning bricks, throwing.
Oh, that's right.
Yeah, they're working
on their bricks.
And some of them are working
in the fields with the farmers.
Each one has his own
job, and his own way.
OK.
And then when I came
closer, and there
was a split between the
boards, put together,
there was openings.
So I could see.
In the back of this van?
In the back-- in the
backyard of that, you see?
Oh, I see.
I see.
You could see through the wall.
Wall, yeah, through the window.
It was boarded up.
Between the boards, you
could see on the other side.
You peeked through.
Right.
And you could see what's there.
And there I saw
standing the three vans.
And on the van naked
people, tied their hands
and on their mouth they
had those taped up.
Taped.
They've been standing
like in a line.
And the smell--
On the street.
Standing in the yard.
In the courtyard or whatever.
Yeah, in that yard.
Then he took him,
picked them up,
and put him down like wood,
one by one, stacked them.
One here, one here,
one here, one here.
They were not living?
Yeah, alive people.
They were standing.
But their hands were
tied in the back.
Well, who picked-- you mean
they were picking up bodily.
Two guys picked them up.
With their legs--
One grabbed them by the legs
and the other like this.
There were women, and
they were, I don't
know if they were old or young.
But I could see the difference
between men and women.
Of course.
Yeah, and they put them
down stacked them like this.
Two this way, and
two on top of them.
And again, they made it
three, sometimes four.
They lay them down, you mean?
Right, like wood.
Yeah, OK.
They grabbed them.
They were tied, their legs
and everything was tied.
And they were standing.
And their mouths were taped,
so there were no sounds.
Right.
And they put them down.
And another guy came in
and threw full of gasoline
on top of them.
You saw this.
Oh, how terrible.
I didn't know what to do.
As soon as I saw that, the
first reaction came to me, now
I know the smell.
That's from Auschwitz,
the corpse smell.
And I went back.
I couldn't move.
I couldn't talk.
And he came in, and he
said what's [NON-ENGLISH]..
He recognized on my face.
He said what happened?
What's going on?
This is your father?
No, my-- the SS.
Oh, I see.
The SS man came back with a dog.
He saw your shock.
He saw me.
You're in the state of shock.
I didn't know what to answer.
So I says, I made like
this, and holding my hand.
And I says the dog
had me [NON-ENGLISH]..
In other words, the dog
almost [NON-ENGLISH] me.
OK.
And he took my hand and looked
down, and said, [NON-ENGLISH]..
Yeah, I says, I took
it away in time.
He have this inside
[NON-ENGLISH]..
That's what I got.
Yeah.
You didn't want to
tell him what you saw.
Right.
He says, [NON-ENGLISH]?
What does that mean?
Did you see anything?
Did you hear anything?
I says, no.
Nothing.
OK.
So he took me in
and came in the camp
back, and came to my father.
And my father saw me.
He says, what's the
matter with you?
So I told him.
I don't know if they are
Jews or who they are.
I don't know.
And I couldn't eat.
I couldn't sleep.
At night, the more
I thought about it,
the more it started
to bother me.
And then it dawned on me
at night, I says, my God.
Can you imagine the pain
those people had to go through
by not even taking away from
them their most human thing
that even you are not
allowed to scream and cry
in your own pain.
You can't do this to
the worst to an animal.
Who are those people?
To this day, I don't know who
they are, and what they are.
I never knew, probably
will never know.
But it went on day after day.
I saw this once.
That was happened one time.
So I assume it went on, because
the smell was constantly there.
The smell was there when I
came there the first time.
Did you see them light
a flame to this gas?
They threw gasoline and
threw a match to it.
Like, that's it.
OK, so how long were did
you stay in this ghetto?
And we were standing like this--
and there was all kinds of
things, smelling and all
of that.
And it was going on,
it's already June.
It has been going on like
this all the way to July.
In August we heard
some shootings going on
and rumors that the Russians
are approaching Warsaw,
and that we will be
liberated by the Russians.
And at one night, we
heard a lot of shooting,
a lot of explosions,
a lot of stuff.
Rumors had it that
the Polish underground
tried to break in, in the
camp and to liberate us.
But they were beaten back
and they couldn't make it.
The next day, I had another
taste of good stuff.
We got up in the morning and
we announced that this lager
will be dissolved.
And we were going to be--
What does that word mean lager?
Lager means camp.
Camp, OK.
That camp will be dissolved.
You're going to be moved again.
And we will be
moved from the camp.
We are going to Germany.
Oh, OK.
But we didn't know that
we were going to walk.
We thought that we
were going to be
taken to transport, you know,
and transport to another camp.
Sure.
We got up in the morning.
We stood there from the
morning from 4 o'clock
till 10:30 at night on the day
outside, no water, no food,
nothing, all day long.
Then we were told to go
back into the barracks.
That was already 18
hours you're standing.
Yeah.
So we went back in.
We went to sleep.
The next day at 4 o'clock
in the morning, again out.
We were standing outside
again all day, sun is shining.
It looked like even heaven
came down against us.
It was a beautiful day, hot
and muggy, and everything.
No water, no nothing.
There is collapsing a guy.
Here is collapsing a guy.
Take him away,
never see him again.
Needless to say, that the
shoving and the screaming
and the hollering what has been
going on is constantly there.
The pushing and the
brutalizing reached a point
where it doesn't matter anymore
with you, because you're
already used to it.
So you take it as an
everyday occurring.
That's the way it is.
It doesn't go any other way.
Finally, the third day
here we are for two days
standing like this outside,
without food, without water,
tired.
They gave you food when
you went into the barrack
at night though.
No, no, nothing.
This is three days with no food.
That's the two
days without food,
without water, or anything.
The third day in the morning,
we got up at 4 o'clock.
We stand outside again
till around 9:00,
9:30 in the morning.
Then they bring in.
We got in line.
Everybody get a Herring, a
salt Herring, a half a bread,
two slices of margarine, and
two slices of cut of jelly,
and a big soup.
And of course, being hungry
and thirsty and everything.
You eat everything, of course.
Eat everything up.
Two hours later, we
are on the march.
We are starting to go.
How everything was
figured out, now the salty
Herring after eating,
everybody eating everything
up, and walking in the heat,
starts to work for water.
Water, water, no water.
Just keep on walking.
Anybody, all of a
sudden you hear.
Psst.
Shot.
Anybody stays behind,
left behind, shot.
Throw it on a wagon.
Some of them, that's
the first days.
The first two days, everybody
got shot was thrown on a wagon.
At night, were buried.
Later on, you didn't even
bother to pick him up anymore.
You just left him on the street.
So you walked for how many days?
Do you remember?
We walked from Warsaw.
We walked to a little
village called Kutna.
It was on the Czechoslovakian
and Polish border.
We walked for almost, let's
see for about between 8 and 10
days.
One day, the fifth day,
we reached a river.
When we got to the river,
everybody jumped in
and drinking water.
We had another encounter.
They had the Gestapo,
not the Gestapo,
but the SS, the
guards and the kapos,
if a guy were there
drinking water,
he just went,
stepped on his neck.
That's the end.
And stood there as
long as he could,
let him, till he
tell suffocated.
Tell me, how many of
you were on this march?
Do you have any idea?
Yes, I will come to that.
We started out close
to 10,000 from Warsaw.
We arrived less
than 8,000 to Kutna.
In Kutna they brought
in again a train.
And this was 10 days later?
Yes.
OK, and the ninth day
without water, God
opened up the heavens
and it started to rain.
I was wet, not my
skin from the outside,
but already from the inside.
Even the heavens
were against us.
And you can imagine how
we have been here sitting
walking and we were
tired, in the throes,
and by a farmer there in
the field outside to rest,
we had to lay down in
the mud and all of this,
and sitting there for two
days, again without food.
Finally, third day
in the morning,
they gave us some
bread and some soup.
We had to go.
The train came.
We had to go in a train,
again, the cattle wagons.
And you don't know
where you're going.
Oh, we don't know.
We only know that
we are by seeing it,
we weren't told where
we are, just what
we could make out from our own
just figuring it out and seeing
where we are.
We saw the sign saying Kutna.
We know that we are in Kutna,
on the border what's what.
And being there for about
a day, after we were
put in, in the wagons.
The wagons were closed.
The doors were locked.
And away we go.
We don't know
where we are going.
My gosh, if this is hell,
if there is hell on Earth,
that sure was hell.
We were about 120 pressed
into a cattle wagon.
And the clothes,
everybody was wet,
and it was sticky
and muddy outside.
And we started the feeling.
And at night, they come in,
and with whips and shooting,
and hitting, and clubbing.
God knows what.
It's dark.
We can't see.
We don't know.
I got hit with--
I don't even know what it was.
In the daytime, I saw the guy
he had a tail from a horse
dried out.
He used it like a whip.
And I got hit with
that on the head.
And in the morning,
we look around there.
Is a guy shot.
There is a guy beaten to death.
There is a guy died.
To make the long story
short, by the time
we arrived from Kutna to
Dachau, which took us all night
and a little bit of the day,
from the 8,000 or so left,
and from beginning
from we arrived 2,000
and some few hundred of us.
Lucky, my father and
my uncle, my uncle
was beaten on the head.
But he was bleeding,
but he survived.
So we arrived in Dachau.
Your father survived this?
Yes, we survived.
We all came in.
But there was others who we
knew didn't make it, friends.
And so why do you think that
the Germans took you away
from that ghetto, because
the Russians were coming,
and they didn't want?
Yes, the Russians already
prepared their attack
against Warsaw.
And it was just approaching.
And they didn't want us
to be liberated by them.
Sure.
They needed you workers.
They wanted you to
continue working.
Right, so they took us back in.
They took us into Dachau.
We arrived to Dachau.
Dachau was already
crowded, because they
started to bring in
from outside the people.
And the first thing they
gave us a shower, to bathe
and took away our clothes.
They took away our clothes
and give us new clothes.
And they gave us a
pair of wooden shoes.
And they let us stay.
They gave us food,
just like for the rest
of the prisoners
in the camp, once
a day water in the morning like
tea, and a soup in the evening,
and all of that.
And we stayed there.
We had where to sleep, at least
like regular barracks and all
of that.
All right.
Let's take a break
again now Larry,
and we'll get back to it, to
the rest of your experiences
in Dachau in a few minutes.
All right.
Let's wait till
the lights go out.